<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-24T13:33:30-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dr. George W. Powell, Ph.D.</title><subtitle>Independent Consulting Agrologist
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Agroforestry - Integrated Benefits of Trees and Shrubs on Farms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/agroforestry-integrated-benefits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agroforestry - Integrated Benefits of Trees and Shrubs on Farms" /><published>2023-11-10T03:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T03:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/agroforestry-integrated-benefits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/agroforestry-integrated-benefits/">&lt;p&gt;The following is a summary of my presentation to the Select Standing Committee on Agriculture, Fish and Food of the Legislative Assembly of British Columbia. My appearance before the Committee and this presentation were part of the Committee’s &lt;em&gt;Consultation on Agricultural Soil and Carbon Sequestration&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-introduction-to-agroforestry&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Agroforestry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aib1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;silvopasture, east Kootenay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an honour to speak to the Committee today about agroforestry, a group of farm practices with tremendous potential to help protect the soil, build soil carbon, and contribute positively to enhancing agricultural production in British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will start today by introducing and defining agroforestry and then highlight some of the prominent agroforestry practices already in use in BC, specifically shelterbelts, silvopastures and farm riparian buffers. I’ll conclude with some priority actions for supporting agroforestry development and adoption in the province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agroforestry is a group of agricultural practices, all of which have in common the intentional, integrated use of trees or shrubs with other crop or livestock production. Agroforestry systems leverage the positive benefits of integration to enhance production, achieve conservation goals, or to buffer and transition land use at the farm or landscape level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is considerable misunderstanding about agroforestry in BC. For clarity therefore, let me emphasize that agroforestry is NOT:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Forestry. It is not woodlots on farms. It does not overlap with forest practices, and this distinction is now laid out in the regulations of the Professional Governance Act.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agroforestry is also not the afforestation of farmland into closed forests, for carbon credits or otherwise.  Agroforestry strategically uses low-density tree and shrub plantings to achieve specific goals. And, indeed it is an unrestricted, permitted farm use within the Agricultural Land Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agroforestry is also not synonymous with non-timber forest products (NTFPs). Some mistakenly equate harvesting mushrooms or floral greenery from forests with agroforestry.  NTFPs are a potential output from some agroforestry settings, but they are not one in the same.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;agroforestrys-strength-for-bc-agriculture&quot;&gt;Agroforestry’s Strength for BC Agriculture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus of the Committee’s consultations is on agricultural soil and carbon sequestration, and agroforestry can, and already is, contributing positively to this. Recent research from the University of Alberta highlights that agroforestry zones can store 46 tonnes per hectare more carbon in above-ground biomass and 36 tonnes per hectare more carbon in the soil than adjacent cropland &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/gcbb.12934&quot;&gt;(An &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. 2022. GCB Bioenergy 14(6):669-680)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real strength of agroforestry however, is as climate change and extreme weather adaptation tool, that generates many co-benefits, including carbon sequestration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelterbelts-and-hedgerows&quot;&gt;Shelterbelts and Hedgerows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aib2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hedgerow, Delta Wildlife and Farmland Trust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll now highlight some agroforestry practices to demonstrate their potential, starting with shelterbelts and hedgerows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have long history of sheltebelt use in Canada, and there are very well documented benefits of using tree and shrub plantings around  and across fields for reducing wind erosion and conserving soil moisture to the benefit crop and livestock production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they do so, while adding carbon storage to farmland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linear plantings of trees and shrubs along fencelines and road edges also present a large opportunity to sequester carbon above and below ground, with no interference to crop production, and indeed many situations where they can enhance yields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statcan.gc.ca/en/census-agriculture&quot;&gt;Census of Agriculture&lt;/a&gt; found 38 percent of farms in BC already use shelterbelts or hedgerows, and their use has grown signifcantly in the last decade, though it still lags the national average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;silvopasture&quot;&gt;Silvopasture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aib3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;silvopasture, Jay Springs Lamb, Pinantan Lake&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second agroforestry practice I’ll highlight is silvopasture: the integration of trees or shrubs with forage production and livestock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent analysis of silvopastures across temperate areas of the world (&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10457-020-00494-6&quot;&gt;Pent, 2020. Agroforest Syst 94: 1741–1758.)&lt;/a&gt;, concluded that it can improve total productivity per area by up to 55 percent compared separating pasture and tree production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, globally, silvopastures are estimated to sink an average of 2.7 tonnes of carbon per hectare, per year &lt;a href=&quot;https://drawdown.org/solutions/silvopasture&quot;&gt;(Project Drawdown)&lt;/a&gt;.  For this reason Project Drawdown, a leading thinktank on climate action, has ranked silvopasture as one of the top fifteen climate mitigation tools on the planet and it is the highest ranked of all of Project Drawdown’s agricultural solutions in terms of mitigation impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production gains on silvopastures, including increased weight gains, milk production and reproductive success, also stem from improved animal welfare &lt;a href=&quot;https://acsess.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1094/FG-2004-1209-01-RV&quot;&gt;(Fike &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, 2004.  Forage and Grazinglands 2(1):1-12.)&lt;/a&gt;. Silvopastures reduce air temperatures and wind speed in their shelter, translating to lower body temperatures and lower water demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happier, healthier animals produce more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silvopastures, as a landscape buffer, offer an option to reduce interface wildfire risks in BC.  Thinning and pruning ingrown forests coupled with targeted grazing is a type of silvopasture. Anecdotal evidence from BC and Washington State supports the effectiveness of silvopastures in slowing or stopping wildfire movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real strength of using silvopastures for fuel management is that it is an option that generates ongoing revenues and economic activity by creating incremental forage production to strengthen livestock sectors. Rejuvination of ingrown community pastures across the BC interior into silvopastures is one such option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many agroforestry systems, this is conservation that pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;farmland-riparian-buffers&quot;&gt;Farmland Riparian Buffers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aib4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;riparian buffer, Lumby&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final agroforestry practice I’ll highlight is farmland riparian buffers. Riparian zones are very productive landscape units where water meets the uplands, and they have incredible potential to sequester carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, work from central Canada found treed riparian buffers can store up to 768 tonnes of carbon per hectare &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.cif-ifc.org/doi/10.5558/tfc2022-012&quot;&gt;(Ofusu &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. 2022. The Forestry Chronicle 98(1):103-118.)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And returning tree and shrub cover to farmland riparian zones comes with many well documented co-benefits including; reduced soil erosion, improved fisheries values, enhanced biodiversity, reduced farm runoff and increased water storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthy riparian zones with deep rooted trees and shrubs, have increased capacity to capture and store water. This acts to slow down the movement of water off-farm and dampen precipitation-driven flood events. This can provide benefits to the farm, where they are experiencing lower water tables due to drought, and also at a watershed level, where upstream banking of water can prevent catastrophic downstream flooding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;priority-development-actions&quot;&gt;Priority Development Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding agroforestry as viable management tool for BC agriculture requires support for the development and adoption of these practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we need to continue to improve awareness and education materials to aid producers in understanding the potential of agroforestry in their individual production settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we need to collect data and analyze basic relationships from existing practices around British Columbia in order to make better data-driven beneficial management practices recommendations and give producers recognition for existing carbon-sinks, often not tabulated in climate modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest strength and challenge to supporting BC agriculture is its diversity. We have hundreds of different production categories carried out in an incredibly diverse array of soils, climate and topography. All of which equates to thousands of unique production settings.  We need to sample across this diversity and pull out the most important factors determining success towards production and conservation goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Shelterbelts" /><category term="Silvopasture" /><category term="Riparian Buffer" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><summary type="html">Agroforestry has tremendous potential to help protect soil, build soil carbon and contribute positively to enhancing agricultural production in British Columbia.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/aib1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/aib1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Agroforestry Book - Trees Against The Wind</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/new-agroforestry-book/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Agroforestry Book - Trees Against The Wind" /><published>2023-09-17T05:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-17T05:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/new-agroforestry-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/new-agroforestry-book/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;trees-against-the-wind-the-birth-of-prairie-shelterbelts&quot;&gt;Trees Against the Wind: The Birth of Prairie Shelterbelts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William R. ‘Bill’ Schroeder has released a new book detailing the history of prairie shelterbelts in Canada. Many people think of that the prairie shelterbelts were a response to the prolonged drought of the &lt;em&gt;Dirty Thirties&lt;/em&gt;, but, as Trees Against the Wind illustrates, this story actually begins much earlier and for different reasons. It is an interesting and enlightening history that increases appreciation for prairie trees and the people who planted them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Others … saw that shelterbelts would improve living conditions on the harsh prairies. Land companies viewed tree planting as a means of making the prairie more appealing to settlers. They believed a good shelterbelt would increase a farm’s value, not only to prospective buyers, but also to future generations, who would enjoy the shade and comfort provided by the trees.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning work at the Prairie Farm Rehabilitation Agency’s Tree Nursery in 1981, Bill discovered the trees he was working with had been brought to the Canadian prairies almost a century earlier as part of a government planting initiative. In spite of the significant challenges involved in growing them in a dry land, the results had been dramatic. Eighty years on, the program was flourishing and open prairie had effectively been transformed into a tapestry of treed farmyards and planted shelterbelts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this book, Schroeder scoured archives in Indian Head, Regina and Ottawa to learn more about the people whose foresight and conviction had made this success possible. With the help of over archival photos and maps, Trees Against the Wind tells the story of the program’s origins, dedicated staff and the thousands of innovative prairie farmers who planted trees to shelter their homes and land. This book provides thought-provoking perspectives on prairie history and a heightened appreciation for the trees in your life, especially those that still grace farmyards and fields, providing valuable biodiversity and habitat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees Against the Wind: The Birth of Prairie Shelterbelts is available from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturesask.ca/publications/trees-against-the-wind&quot;&gt;Nature Saskatchewan’s online store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please note: I have NOT received any compensation for helping to promote this book, nor am I participating in an affiliate link program should you order this publication by following the links on this website. Text included in this post was provided by Bill Schroeder and Nature Saskatchewan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Shelterbelts" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><summary type="html">Bill Schroeder has released a new book on the interesting history of prairie shelterbelts in Canada.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/treesagainstthewind.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/treesagainstthewind.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Silvopasture Knowledge Transfer Plan</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/silvopasture/silvopasture-ktp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silvopasture Knowledge Transfer Plan" /><published>2023-01-20T04:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T04:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/silvopasture/silvopasture-ktp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/silvopasture/silvopasture-ktp/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;December 15, 2022, UPDATE&lt;/strong&gt; Thank you for your interest in the Silvopasture Knowledge Transfer Plan.  Stakeholder input is now closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 20, 2023, UPDATE&lt;/strong&gt; The Silvopasture Knowledge Transfer Plan is complete.  Thank you to all who provided input. For access to the completed document, please contact the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.gov.bc.ca/gov/content/industry/agriculture-seafood/agricultural-land-and-environment/agroforestry&quot;&gt;British Columbia Ministry of Agriculture and Food (AF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-participation-is-welcomed&quot;&gt;Your Participation is Welcomed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Columbia Ministry of Agriculture and Food (AF) is developing a Five-Year Knowledge Transfer Plan for Silvopasture in BC. I’m pleased to be coordinating the development of this plan under the direction of a diverse and knowledgeable project steering committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have experience in using silvopastoral methods, or an interest in learning more about silvopasture? Your input would be welcomed into the development of the Knowledge Transfer Plan. Start by completing one of the two surveys listed below. One is designed for producers (agricultural, woodlot managers, both new or experienced). The second is designed primarily for professionals (Agrologists, Biologists, Foresters and Planners) in British Columbia that use, or are interested in using silvopastoral practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assist AF in developing this plan your participation is welcomed in an online survey to help better understand your interests, aspirations, concerns and priorities. These surveys will allow AF to profile silvopasture production practices and interests throughout BC and understand your motivation for using silvopasture. The surveys will allow you to rate support topics and support methods: how you prefer to learn and receive information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey should take no more than 30 minutes to complete. Please feel free to pass these links onto others in BC with an interest in improved access to silvopasture information and support. The surveys will be open until August 31, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before completing the survey, you can review some general information on &lt;a href=&quot;/silvopasture/silvopasture-in-bc/&quot;&gt;silvopasture in BC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interviews-and-focus-groups&quot;&gt;Interviews and Focus Groups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to provide additional assistance and share your interests and ideas please participate in an interview or a focus group. Interviews will begin this summer and focus groups will be held in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To participate in an interview or focus group please use the site’s contact form to provide your name, email address and phone number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notice-of-collection-of-information&quot;&gt;Notice of Collection of Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey responses are intended to be anonymous, and data will be used in amalgamated form only. The purpose of the survey is to assist the BC Ministry of Agriculture and Food in developing a Five-Year Knowledge-Transfer Plan for Silvopasture. Participants are also needed for interviews and focus groups to help identify and provide direction on the development of new silvopasture communication approaches and products for BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wish to further participate in development of the Knowledge Transfer Plan, you will be asked to submit contact information at the end of the survey (through a web link). It is optional for you to provide contact information. Your contact information is collected under section 26(c) and 26(e) of the Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act for the purposes explained above. Contact information provided will not be used to associate your identity with your survey responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;personal-information-reminder&quot;&gt;Personal Information Reminder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do enter personal details/information in the survey. If you wish to provide contact information to participate further in this project, you will be directed (through a web link) to a new form to submit your contact information. Otherwise, if personal information is provided it will be removed to maintain anonymity and use of the information in aggregated form only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding for the development of the Five-Year Knowledge Transfer Plan for Silvopasture has been provided by the Canadian Agricultural Partnership – a federal-provincial-territorial initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/CAP.png&quot; alt=&quot;CAP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Silvopasture" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><summary type="html">A knowledge transfer plan is being developed for extending information on the use of silvopasture in British Columbia (BC) for production and conservation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SP_KTP.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SP_KTP.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trees on Farms in British Columbia - Updated</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/trees-on-farms-in-british-columbia-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trees on Farms in British Columbia - Updated" /><published>2022-05-12T18:21:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-12T18:21:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/trees-on-farms-in-british-columbia-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/trees-on-farms-in-british-columbia-2021/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Updated and revised May 12, 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday saw the first release of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statcan.gc.ca/en/census-agriculture&quot;&gt;2021 Census of Agriculture&lt;/a&gt; data in Canada. A veritable feast of agricultural information is now being served up to the inner statistician in all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This again provided an opportunity to check up on the use of trees on British Columbia (BC) farms for production and conservation. Unfortunately, there are still no statistics gathered to help us determine what management systems are employed on farms. Hence, the numbers presented here represent the use of trees in a blend of conventional horticulture, farm forestry and agroforestry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trees-on-farms-infographic-300x226.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trees on Farms Infographic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tree-fruit-and-nut-production-increases&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tree Fruit and Nut Production Increases&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When classed by the North American Industry Classification System (NAICS), there are now 3,036 farms, representing 19% of all BC farms, categorized as fruit or tree nut producers. This is up from 17% in 2011 and 18% in 2016. The proportion of tree fruit and nut farms in BC is also well ahead of the national average of just under 4% of all farms. These numbers however, also include a significant number of berry producers (e.g. blueberry, raspberry) concentrated in the Lower Mainland region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In specific tree fruit categories, BC has 3,484 ha planted to apples (an 11% decline from 2016), 226 ha in pears (13% decline from 2016), 180 ha of plums (6% decline from 2016), 2,851 ha of sweet cherries (43% increase from 2016), 65 ha of sour cherries (55% increase from 2016), 520 ha of peaches (nominal decrease from 2016) and 70 ha of apricots (a big decrease of 29% from 2016). These tree fruit orchards represent 20, 29, 29, 95, 8, 21 and 64%, respectively, of the total national plantings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/image-1-300x195.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fruit trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tree fruit production in BC is still highly concentrated within the Okanagan and surrounding southern interior valleys. The Okanagan-Similkameen and Central Okanagan Regional Districts account for approximately one-third of the provincial tree fruit and nut farms. And this represents 88% of the total area in BC planted planted to tree fruits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domestic markets are important for fruit and nut sales, but export markets are on the rise. The large expansion over the past 10 years in sweet cherry plantings can be almost wholly attributed to exports to asia where demand remains strong for these high quality soft fruits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forest-products-sales&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forest Products Sales?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forest product sales from BC farms rose over 40% from 2011 to 2016 to $6.3 million. This represents about 9% of the total sales of forest products from farmland across Canada. A large increase in raw log sales from farms reflect, in part, shrinking supplies from Crown lands. And this is due, in part, to where the mountain pine beetle has run its course and salvage harvest volumes are declining. Overall however, wood sales from farms in BC remains a very small proportion of the total annual timber harvest. And sales from farmland have not yet rebounded to pre-pine beetle levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Stats Can, in their infinite lack of wisdom, no longer tracks farm forest product sales. An important revenue source for many BC farmers and ranchers, but doesn’t fit in the ‘agriculture silo’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;non-timber-forest-production-declining&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-timber Forest Production Declining&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production of non-timber forest products (NTFPs) on BC farms has weakened significantly since 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;christmas-trees&quot;&gt;Christmas Trees&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total number of BC farms growing Christmas trees has declined by 45%, and the area planted by 52% in the last decade. Total farm area dedicated to Christmas trees now sits at 1,272 ha. But importantly, from a total industry standpoint, this does not include the areas of public lands in BC used for Christmas tree harvest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These declines in Christmas tree production coincided with explosive demand for real trees over the past two years with equally strong improvements in direct to consumer pricing. The decline in Christmas tree farms may reflect a producer demographic ‘headwind’ for the sector. Many tree growers have retired from the business in the past 10 years, and new entrants are not replacing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/image-2-300x226.png&quot; alt=&quot;Native stand Douglas-fir Christmas trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;maple-syrup&quot;&gt;Maple Syrup&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BC’s once promising bigleaf maple tapping sector shrank considerably in the last census period. The number of farms reporting maple taps decreased by nearly 60% from 76 to 31 farms, concentrated heavily on Vancouver Island and the Lower Mainland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of spiles employed was 4009 in 2016, and was not released in the latest Census because of the small number of farm operations engaged in this sector. Overall, the number of maple spiles in BC only accounts for a tiny fraction of the Canadian total (dominated in Quebec and Ontario). Bigleaf maple syrup insiders also note the number of small-scale producers tapping for their own consumption. This is not captured in the Census data, and could be in the hundreds on Vancouver Island and the Gulf Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/image-3-150x150.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tapping bigleaf maple&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;farm-trees-for-conservation-continues-to-expand&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Farm Trees for Conservation Continues to Expand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of shelterbelts, hedgerows and windbreaks on BC farms (both natural and planted) continues to expand at a rapid pace. Over 38% of BC farms now employ shelterbelts. This is a relative increase of 95% in the use of this conservation / agroforestry practice from 2011 to 2021. But BC still lags the national average, with over 52% of all Canadian farms now using shelterbelts or windbreaks. BC Peace River regional farms still have significantly higher use of shelterbelts than elsewhere in the province. Approximately 71% of farms in the Peace River and Northern Rockies Regional Districts report adopting this practice. But other districts are catching up, notably the Cariboo with 56%, and the Nechako with over 58% of farms using agroforestry for conservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All raw data used in the preparation of this article has been derived from the Statistics Canada’s Census of Agriculture for 2011 through 2021. Tables 32-10-0161-01, 32-10-0164-01, 32-10-0231-01, 32-10-0249-01, 32-10-0315-01 and 32-10-0369-01 were used.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><category term="Conservation" /><category term="Non-timber Forest Resources" /><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><category term="British Columbia" /><category term="Christmas tree" /><category term="Conservation" /><category term="forest farming" /><category term="land use" /><category term="non-timber forest products" /><category term="Shelterbelts" /><category term="windbreak" /><summary type="html">A check up on the use of trees on British Columbia (BC) farms for production and conservation</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/trees-on-farms-in-BC-768x536.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/trees-on-farms-in-BC-768x536.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Soaring Land Costs and the Future of the Family Farm</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/soaring-land-costs-and-the-future-of-the-family-farm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Soaring Land Costs and the Future of the Family Farm" /><published>2022-03-17T11:46:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-17T11:46:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/soaring-land-costs-and-the-future-of-the-family-farm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/soaring-land-costs-and-the-future-of-the-family-farm/">&lt;p&gt;Farm Credit Canada’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fcc-fac.ca/en/knowledge/economics/farmland-values-report.html&quot;&gt;annual report on farm values&lt;/a&gt; revealed soaring farmland costs across the country in 2021. This is good news if you are intending on liquidating your farm holdings. But bad news if you are trying to get started in agriculture and for society as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;record-high-land-costs&quot;&gt;Record High Land Costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across Canada farmland prices increased by 8.3 percent in 2021. In British Columbia, it was a whopping 18.1 percent rise. And, in some BC regions the jump was even more acute. For example, farmland values in the South Coast region rose by 33.7 percent, and by 28.2 percent in the Cariboo-Chilcotin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trend of ever more costly farmland has been in place for more than a decade. In fact, Canadian farmland prices have posted an average annual increase of 10.8 percent since 2012. This far outpaces inflation. And, it has profound implications for the future of the family farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/FCCimage-768x370.png&quot; alt=&quot;Farm Credit Canada Farmland Values Report 2021&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farm operators (aka farmers and ranchers) are getting older. Their average age was 55 as of the 2016 census of agriculture release. Many are part of the post-world war baby boom generation. And as they look to retirement, for the most part, younger generations are taking a pass on replacing them. This lack of recruitment poses a serious challenge to the long-term viability of agriculture in BC and all of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in order to bring on a new generation of farmers and ranchers there needs to be some hope of making a good living. But that is not the case for many. For example, a recent survey conducted by the Small Scale Meat Producers of BC found 37 percent of their sector operate at a loss. Another 29 percent only break-even. And, almost all (96 percent) of these small-scale family farms rely on off-farm income to supplement their farm gate sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This too is not a new phenomenon. Agriculture has always been a low margin, high capital cost endeavor. But generations of family farms still built wealth through capital gains. Farming, supplemented by off-farm income, generates cash flow to keep the creditors at bay. The pay off in farming and ranching has come in the form of long-term asset appreciation. Gains in the value of breeding herds, maturing timber, farm infrastructure and the land itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you might conclude that soaring farmland values are good for farmers because it means a bigger payoff for years of work. Indeed, this is good news if you are intending on liquidating your farm holdings. But it is bad news if you are trying to get started in agriculture. And thus bad for the sector in light of the difficulties of recruiting new entrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-new-land-rush&quot;&gt;The New Land Rush&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past two decades farmland has become a desired ‘asset class’ among investors. This has been coupled with cheap money stemming from the hyper-inflationary monetary policies of the Bank of Canada. And, as a result, investors bidding up the price of farmland beyond what would be expected based on its intrinsic value to produce food and other goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In British Columbia, not all farmland is created equal. Valley bottoms and southern geographies tend to have more productive land because of superior climate and soils. But this intrinsic value has been greatly distorted by proximity to major urban centres. This is true even though the Agricultural Land Reserve provides a measure of protection from conversion of farmland to non-farm uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, farmland around greater Vancouver now costs an average of $134,700 per acre. Land in northern BC sells for an average of $2,100 per acre. Lower Mainland farms are more productive and can produce a wider range of crops than in the north. But they are not 60 times more productive than northern BC farmland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emerging-neofeudalism&quot;&gt;Emerging Neofeudalism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who are interested in agriculture, but are not fortunate enough to inherit land, now face a monumental hurdle to owning a farm. And a tenant farming system is emerging for new farm operators who increasingly must turn to land leasing and rental options. That is, when they are even available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenant farmers still take on the all the agricultural production and market risks, sometimes with little or no profit. But their landlords capture all of the value creation through land appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hollowing out of agriculture and loss of family farms will lead us to new form of feudalism. And this has profound implications for rural economies and social structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agriculture, dominated by family farms, has been the backbone of the Province of BC. It has a stabilizing effect the boom and bust cycles of forestry, mining and recently tourism. Agriculture also reinforces circularity in regional economies. The farmers and ranchers of BC, for the most part, earn and spend their income where they live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing corporate ownership of the land and loss of family farms can turn this upside down. Corporate ownership takes its profits to Bay Street and beyond. It also doesn’t need nor necessarily support rural jobs. Without local owner operators, large corporate farms increasingly rely on temporary foreign labour. And it doesn’t even care if the farmland it owns is farmed. Many would be just as happy to collect ‘ecological goods and services’ credits from the government or environmental NGOs for not farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this can lead to even greater reliance on food imports, with associated diminshment of our independence, rural social fabric and food security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/scroll.png&quot; alt=&quot;comments&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-comments-on-soaring-land-costs&quot;&gt;Three comments on “Soaring Land Costs…”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devin&lt;/strong&gt; 19 March 2022 at 9:21 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Great post. Well thought out and presented. How do you think climate change will impact farm prices?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Devin)&lt;/strong&gt; 19 March 2022 at 9:47 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks taking time to read and comment Devin.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The impacts of climate change on BC will vary by region. In some regions it could definitely diminish the productive capacity of farms and that would lower the land’s value for farming. For example, increasing flood frequency in the Fraser Valley is either going to drive up individual costs for insurance and repairs, or it will cost hundreds of millions to put in appropriate regional diking and drainage infrastructure. The closer you get to the delta, a higher risk of salt water incursion onto farmland comes into play from rising sea levels. And large areas of farmland in the southern interior will only be suited to seasonal livestock grazing unless water rights and irrigation are in place. Rain-fed agriculture is becoming a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;On the flip side, net-net, farmland in the central interior and northern BC will likely have increased productivity due to an improving climate. The winters are getting shorter and milder. That means a longer growing season and wider range of crops that can be profitably grown with better yields.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, given that one my main arguements is that farmland prices have decoupled to a large degree from the productivity of the land, perhaps it is all moot. I think macro factors outside of agriculture (e.g. monetary policy) are driving the price appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Douglas Chen&lt;/strong&gt; 13 April 2022 at 3:26 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Canadian monetary policy is on its turning point. Seems to me, productivity and access to a sustainable market are more fundamental factors than land costs and funding the young farmers shall consider before committing themselves to a farming life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;comments-are-closed&quot;&gt;Comments are closed.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="British Columbia" /><category term="economics" /><category term="Food Security" /><category term="land costs" /><category term="land use" /><summary type="html">In the past two decades farmland has become a desired ‘asset class’ among investors. This has been coupled with cheap money stemming from the hyper-inflationary monetary policies of the Bank of Canada. And, as a result, investors bidding up the price of farmland beyond what would be expected based on its intrinsic value to produce food and other goods.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Reeve_and_Serfs-768x443.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Reeve_and_Serfs-768x443.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Agricultural Ignorance and Apathy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/agricultural-ignorance-and-apathy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agricultural Ignorance and Apathy" /><published>2022-02-10T11:45:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-10T11:45:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/agricultural-ignorance-and-apathy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/agricultural-ignorance-and-apathy/">&lt;p&gt;Frank Layden, former coach of the NBA’s Utah Jazz, once recounted a conversation he had with an underperforming player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I told him, ‘Son, what is it with you? Is it &lt;em&gt;ignorance&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;apathy&lt;/em&gt;?’ He said, ‘Coach, I don’t know, and I don’t care’.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Los Angeles Times, December 10, 1988&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Frank_Layden_1988-89.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank Layden, c. 1988&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is the two-headed monster of public ignorance and apathy that creates one of the greatest challenges to agriculture. And, indeed, also for society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently agriculture has been prominent in the news. And rightly so. It is foundational to human health and survival. It is woven into many of our most pressing environmental and socio-economic issues. Yet, move beyond the recent concerns about food inflation and grocery store supply disruptions and very few people seem to care about the viability of Canadian agriculture. Indeed in last fall’s federal election, neither agriculture nor food directly ranked among &lt;a href=&quot;https://angusreid.org/federal-election-top-issues/&quot;&gt;the top ten voter issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do we develop a long-term, supportive public policy for sustainable agriculture? Especially when the majority of the public knows very little about the subject and doesn’t care to learn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;roots-of-the-problem&quot;&gt;Roots of the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the roots of the apathy, you have to delve into the psyche of western societies. The past five centuries have been marked by a steady of procession of globalization: expansion, industrialization and urbanization. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2021/dp-pd/index-eng.cfm&quot;&gt;Canada’s recently released 2021 population statistics&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate this trend. Roughly 85 percent of the country now lives in urban centres. And this number increases every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/can-population-split.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rural-Urban Divide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through the generations, most urban people have developed an attitude of superiorty through majority. Even if subconsciencely, most people equate moving away from life on the land to progress. And by extension, agriculture is not important because it is primarily not urban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the lived experience of working the land, most people don’t recognize agriculture as an interface between humanity and the planet. As such, farming and ranching has been devalued over time. And as a consequence most people can only relate to agriculture through one of its outputs: food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments and institutions increasingly reflect this limited connection to agriculture. It’s found in the language they use. Governments favour supporting ‘food hubs’ over of agriculture centres. Universities rebrand faculties of agriculture to ‘food systems’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to suggest that food is unimportant. But when you value products more than the processes that create and sustain them, you become divorced from the real connections of humans to ecosystems. And the ‘I want cheap food and convenient access’ trumps supporting agriculture as a form of applied ecology. Therefore, this attitude obscures agriculture’s links to human health, wealth and survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lack-of-engagement&quot;&gt;Lack of Engagement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At best, public indifference means farmers don’t have to contend with deep, time consuming policy debates. They can engage directly with the policy makers and hope they understand the issues experienced at the farm level. At worst, one must battle with shallow knowledge that is easily swayed by a meme-driven, sound-byte culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mental distinction between food and agriculture also leads to the public as not seeing themselves as being directly part of agricultural issues. For example, more than 30 percent of food gets wasted at the retail and consumer levels. This waste is more impactful on greenhouse gas emissions, water use and displacement of habitats than any individual agricultural practice. Yet few people tipping their left-overs into the trash see themselves as at the heart of agriculture’s environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shallow thinking is also reflected in the hypocrisy of over-regulating and restricting local agriculture on ‘environmental grounds’. All the while, importing food from elsewhere. This is tantamount to outsourcing the environmental impacts of your food. And it limits the ability to work collaboratively on solving some of the most challenging agri-environmental issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solutions&quot;&gt;Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In crisis there is always opportunity. And the present abundance of climate-driven crises serve up an opportunity to re-engage the public in a deeper level of understanding and connection to agricultural issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand that advancing this discussion is a process, and not a one-time event. Indeed, the rural-urban divide is not new, but it has widened with the parabolic urban population growth. Bridging the divide will not be a short-term endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solutions start with youth. Support and expand the highly successful ‘Agriculture in the Classroom‘ programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education of adults is also key. Expand opportunities for consumers to speak with producers at farmers’ markets and retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encourging people to grow some of their own food also, even if the volume generated is symbolic, creates real connections to agriculture. Community gardens and forest gardens are important outlets for this activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, educate politicians and policy makers until there is broader societal understanding. They should be a bridge between the huge urban element and the rural minority. Farmers and ranchers simply no longer have the voting power to keep agricultural issues in the mainstream. But democracy does not need to be a tyranny of the majority.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Food Security" /><category term="land use" /><category term="Policy" /><category term="population" /><category term="urban-rural" /><summary type="html">The two-headed monster of public ignorance and apathy that creates one of the greatest challenges to agriculture. And, indeed, also for society.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Agricultural-Ignorance-and-Apathy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Agricultural-Ignorance-and-Apathy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Tribute to Pete Spencer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/a-tribute-to-pete-spencer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tribute to Pete Spencer" /><published>2021-12-28T11:06:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-28T11:06:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/a-tribute-to-pete-spencer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/a-tribute-to-pete-spencer/">&lt;p&gt;Most of the people I have met in my life have not left an impression. Our encounters now reside in the back corners of my mind as a face or name that is disconnected from where or when we interacted. Others, for better or worse, or sheer volume of discourse, have resonated with me. And then there are a select few, for whom I’m a better person for having known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete Spencer was such a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first met Pete years ago when I facilitated the British Columbia Agroforestry Initiative. He had moved from ranching and logging in Vanderhoof to an acreage in Kelowna. He was planting Christmas trees and was looking for advice and connections. I soon realized that he knew a great deal more about agroforestry than his initial questions implied. And, from this first meeting onwards, I came to know Pete as someone who was humble, wise and giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010 I joined on with the Environmental Farm Plan (EFP) Program as a Planning Advisor. It was my great fortune to have Pete assigned to me as a mentor and to guide me through my first EFP. Pete had been with the Program since its inception in BC in 2004. His dedication to both agriculture and conservation were deep and unshakable. Prior to my first solo, on-farm EFP we had coffee together for a final briefing session. He told me he felt like he had nothing worthwhile to teach me. But I assured him that my many years in universities would be of secondary importance to gaining his people skills. Conservation is much more of social process than technical or scientific. And in the agricultural realm, Pete Spencer was peerless in bringing people together around a common goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete was pragmatic man who could always see a solution on the ground, through the foggy, chaotic melieu that land use planning can be in British Columbia. He was a master of finding compromises and building consensus. He approached ever situation with a warm smile, a handshake and an open mind. Always ready to make the best of whatever situation he faced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete listened to everyone. And he didn’t enter a room with his own agenda, other than trying to find a workable solution for all involved. Where others come to meetings to press some perceived advantage or pivot the conversation to present a sales job on their own pet project, Pete Spencer first listened and then questioned to gain understanding from all involved before offering his opinions. He was a master of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete was a champion for conserving streams, rivers, riparian habitats, species-at-risk and other natural values. In so doing, he often had to convey some hard realities to growers, farmers and ranchers about their agricultural practices. But he was gifted in finding solutions that helped them both steward their land and sustain their production. Taking land out of agricultural production for a preserve or a park is easy. Pete chose to work the harder ground of promoting farming and ranching that sustains natural functions and food production alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our early conversations and through many professional interactions, my respect for Pete grew with each meeting. As time passed, we would frequently exchange ideas or serve as each other’s sounding board when we encountered novel situations. Pete’s generousity with his time was seemingly boundless. He was deeply involved within and outside his community. And he was always trying to do his part to make things better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete was also a man of great humour. It was a joy to be with him when he shared anecdotes and jokes over drinks. He had a remarkable gift to be able to find the lighter side of every situation, however challenging. Pete was a light-hearted, roll-with-punches kind of man. And his good humour and ever pleasant demeanor is what I will remember the most about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete, my friend, you will be dearly missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/scroll.png&quot; alt=&quot;comments&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twenty-one-comments-on-a-tribute-to-pete-spencer&quot;&gt;Twenty-one comments on “A Tribute to Pete Spencer”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rob Dinwoodie&lt;/strong&gt; 29 December 2021 at 9:01 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;George that is certainly a fitting tribute to a man we all loved and shared a common desire to be good stewards of the land. Thanks for sharing your story about Pete and I like you and many others will truly miss him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Rob Dinwoodie)&lt;/strong&gt; 30 December 2021 at 9:43 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thank you for sharing your thoughts Rob. Pete truly was a stalwart of agriculture and conservation in BC, and on a personal level, he was a kind, generous man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jaclyn Laic&lt;/strong&gt; 30 December 2021 at 9:00 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m so sorry to hear this. A lovely tribute George. What a sad loss for agriculture and for all who knew him. Walking farms with Pete was an incredible experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mike Simpson&lt;/strong&gt; 30 December 2021 at 10:00 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sad to hear of Pete’s passing. I agree with George’s assessment of Pete, I always enjoyed my interactions with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Darren Brown, PhD&lt;/strong&gt; 30 December 2021 at 10:43 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A kind man with much wisdom to share. He definitely loved the work he did in agriculture and was revered among farmers and his peers. Sorry to hear of his passing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicole Pressey&lt;/strong&gt; 30 December 2021 at 5:00 pm via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A well written tribute. Thank you for sharing George.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reg Steward&lt;/strong&gt; 1 January 2022 at 11:19 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Loss of a great advocate and friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lani French&lt;/strong&gt; 1 January 2022 at 7:17 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am so sorry to hear of Petes passing. He was a man that was always eager to answer any questions, and make agriculture more respectable. Pete always had a smile and positive thoughts. Our industry will have a huge void in it without Pete. He will be missed …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Lani French)&lt;/strong&gt; 2 January 2022 at 9:15 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thank you for taking time to leave a comment Lani. Pete’s tireless work and dedication to agriculture has had a positive impact on so many across the Province.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geoff Hughes-Games&lt;/strong&gt; 5 January 2022 at 11:27 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;George, so well written, thank-you for sharing. I first met Pete in October 2003 at one of the first Planning Advisor training sessions. I knew then that I had met a remarkable individual. Like you, I learned so much from his quiet and thoughtful demeanor. Our discussions about issues faced by farmers and ranchers were always enjoyable, although the path we might have taken to achieve a solution was often different, our goal was still the same. He will be sorely missed but will live on in my memory as an ecologist and gentleman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Geoff Hughes-Games)&lt;/strong&gt; 5 January 2022 at 12:34 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Couldn’t agree more Geoff. Part of Pete’s legacy is in the many people he has positively impacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carl Withler&lt;/strong&gt; 7 January 2022 at 10:48 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I met Pete in 2004 when he wandered into my office in Kelowna while I was the Regional Agrologist for the Ministry of Agriculture………..didn’t take long for me to like Pete…..he had a great sense of humour, great life/farming experiences and made me comfortable in sharing our collective knowledge together…….his was always greater than mine. I will miss Pete and currently have a spruce tree in my bakyard that he gave my sons when we visited his tree farm…….it is a nice reminder of a great human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Carl Withler)&lt;/strong&gt; 7 January 2022 at 4:19 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks for sharing and adding to Pete’s tribute Carl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duane Holder&lt;/strong&gt; 7 January 2022 at 7:17 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;George. That was a great tribute and I am so sorry to hear of his loss. I always felt so fortunate to have known Pete and was always thankful for his willingness to share his knowledge. He had the ability to make us all better stewards of the land and I think would define the meaning of common sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Duane Holder)&lt;/strong&gt; 7 January 2022 at 10:59 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thank you Duane. I sincerely think we all feel fortunate for having known Pete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Todd Cashin&lt;/strong&gt; 11 January 2022 at 8:44 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fantastic tribute to a beauty of a man. Thanks George!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I first met Pete 20 years ago on an Environmental Farm Plan project on Joe Rich Creek. He was a strong voice for both the rancher and for the much-needed restoration along this little stretch of riparian area.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Years later, I was the staff liaison for the City of Kelowna’s Agricultural Advisory Committee when I came across Pete’s application for the committee. As you can imagine, Pete was a welcomed voice on that committee and subsequently provided years of great input to staff, committee members and to City Council.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Pete was a friend, colleague and mentor of mine for many years and I never thanked him for that. Thank you Pete!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wesley Miles (responding to Todd Cashin)&lt;/strong&gt; 11 January 2022 at 11:47 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well said Todd. Pete was always a pleasure to work with and his calm guidance and knowledge was very much appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alan Bates (responding to Todd Cashin)&lt;/strong&gt; 12 January 2022 at 3:24 pm via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I guess I first met Pete at the same time and place as you Todd, and have worked with him many times since. He was always a pleasure to work with and get things done effectively and appropriately. He was one guy you were always happy to talk to. I am sorry to hear of his passing and I will miss working with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alison Speirs&lt;/strong&gt; 25 January 2022 at 11:53 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well written George! All of us from the EFP/BMP program miss Pete. He was always willing to step up and help bring on the new Planning Advisors into the program. The thing that stands out for me is Pete’s way of speaking to others, always interested, and always willing to share what he knew…. I can still hear him complaining about the new technology (i.e. Zoom presentations!!) and how his computer was not cooperating! It’s such a loss…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;George Powell (responding to Alison Speirs)&lt;/strong&gt; 8 November 2010 at 10:22 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thank you Alison for sharing and adding to Pete’s tribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heather Carriere&lt;/strong&gt; 28 January 2022 at 11:31 am via LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m so sad to hear of his passing. He was a valued colleague and friend in the EFP program. He will be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;comments-are-closed&quot;&gt;Comments are closed.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Conservation" /><category term="General" /><category term="British Columbia" /><category term="Celebration of Life" /><category term="Conservation" /><category term="environmental farm plan" /><category term="Kelowna" /><category term="Pete Spencer" /><category term="Vanderhoof" /><summary type="html">Most of the people I have met in my life have not left an impression. Our encounters now reside in the back corners of my mind as a face or name that is disconnected from where or when we interacted. Others, for better or worse, or sheer volume of discourse, have resonated with me. And then there are a select few, for whom I’m a better person for having known.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Pete-Spencer-300x184.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Pete-Spencer-300x184.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Agricultural Water Policy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/agricultural-water-policy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agricultural Water Policy" /><published>2021-06-07T11:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-07T11:02:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/agricultural-water-policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/agricultural-water-policy/">&lt;p&gt;The need for a clear agricultural water policy in British Columbia has never been greater. Without access to water, there will be no agriculture. But that does not mean that the agricultural community should not work towards improving food security with efficient and responsible water use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video is of a panel discussion I partipated in looking at agricultural water policy in the Cariboo and Okanagan regions of British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the panel we discussed some of the challenges of meeting the goals of the Water Sustainability Act. I emphasized the need to be proactive and develop integrated, ‘win-win’ solutions. Policy should focus on education and incentives for water conservation and climate adaptation. Policy focused solely on a regulatory approach will not solve British Columbia’s water challenges, nor any other complex social issues of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discussion was part of a series on agricultural water policy challenges in a changing climate. This webinar series was sponsored by UBC Okanagan and the Agricultural Climate Adaptation Research Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MS2D4jtF7pQ?feature=oembed&quot; title=&quot;Agricultural water policy in the Cariboo and Okanagan, BC&quot; width=&quot;640&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Conservation" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><category term="climate action" /><category term="Climate Change" /><category term="Policy" /><category term="soil organics" /><category term="water" /><category term="water conservation" /><category term="Water Sustainability Act" /><summary type="html">The need for a clear agricultural water policy in British Columbia has never been greater. Without access to water, there will be no agriculture. But that does not mean that the agricultural community should not work towards improving food security with efficient and responsible water use.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Agricultural-Water-Policy-1-768x548.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Agricultural-Water-Policy-1-768x548.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Silvopasture in British Columbia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/silvopasture/silvopasture-in-bc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silvopasture in British Columbia" /><published>2021-01-01T04:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T04:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/silvopasture/silvopasture-in-bc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/silvopasture/silvopasture-in-bc/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Indigenous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indigenous-origins&quot;&gt;Indigenous Origins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indigenous people in the area now bounded by British Columbia have used fire for thousands of years to remove tree and shrub cover. This land management was done, in part, to improve grazing values. First for native ungulates that could be hunted, later for both wildlife and horses. This traditional use is the earliest expression of silvopasture principles in B.C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Multifunctional&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multifunctional-resource-management&quot;&gt;Multifunctional Resource Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British Columbia has a long history of integrating multiple resources and natural values on Crown Lands. Since the mid- 1950s, millions of hectares of regenerating forest land held under forest licences are also used for transient, sustainable grazing opportunities. These compatible resource uses are also managed to conserve and sustain a wide variety of natural values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Diverse&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diversification&quot;&gt;Diversification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmers, ranchers and woodlot managers manage their production and market risks by blending tree and shrub production with forage and livestock. Diverse production contributes to the long-term stability of rural economies in British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Watershed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;watershed-stewardship&quot;&gt;Watershed Stewardship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British Columbia’s award winning &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-uMsR5UN3xY&quot;&gt;silvopasture demonstration&lt;/a&gt; at Vernon Creek in the North Okanagan is showing how cooperation and an integrated approach can improve water quality and watershed values, while maintaining forest and forage production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Efficient&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;efficient-land-use-1--1--2&quot;&gt;Efficient Land Use: 1 + 1 &amp;gt; 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blending deep-rooted trees and shrubs with shallow rooted forage and browse species makes better use of soil nutrients and available water. Multiple canopy layers produce achieve efficiencies in capturing the available light. Intercropping makes full use of the land and can result in over-yielding. Silvopastoral production per unit land can exceed the sum of separate production areas for each crop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wildfire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;managing-wildfire-risks&quot;&gt;Managing Wildfire Risks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silvopastures have lower tree densities and less ladder fuels than unmanaged forests. Grazing helps prevent the build up of fine fuels on the ground layer. Silvopastures, therefore, offer a management option to create zones of lowered wildfire risk that can be deployed to lower the risks of catastrophic wildfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Climate Change&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;climate-change&quot;&gt;Climate Change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silvopastures can help to both mitigate and adapt to a changing climate. Trees and shrubs are largely composed of woody materials. Each ton of wood is approximately 50% stored carbon. Trees and shrubs also help farmers and ranchers adapt to warmer and drier conditions. Shade slows evaporation of water from the soil and forage quality is extended when grown under a partial canopy relative to hot, dry openings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SPBC8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Animal Welfare&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animal-welfare&quot;&gt;Animal Welfare&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tree and shrub canopies in silvopastures buffer livestock from climate extremes. Shade provides cool relief in the summer, and thermal cover protects animals from wind and cold temperatures over winter. Lowered animal stress contributes to better herd health and production.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Silvopasture" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><summary type="html">Examples of how silvopasture is used in British Columbia (BC) for production and conservation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SPBC1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SPBC1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Soil Tilth and Organics for Water Conservation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/soil-tilth-and-organics-for-water-conservation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Soil Tilth and Organics for Water Conservation" /><published>2020-10-16T08:13:08-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T08:13:08-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/soil-tilth-and-organics-for-water-conservation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/soil-tilth-and-organics-for-water-conservation/">&lt;p&gt;Adapting to a changing climate will be one of the key factors to the future success of agriculture. Water conservation in farm settings should start with building the capacity of the land to capture and retain precipitation. Improving tilth and adding organic matter to soils are effective tools for water management. Enhancing water capture and storage in the soil can be a cost-effective solution to minimizing drought impacts in dryland farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video presentation was the final of three that I made to the 2020 Water Management Strategies for Dryland Agriculture Webinar Series. The webinar series was sponsored by the BC Agriculture and Food Climate Action Initiative. It was delivered as part of their regional adaptation program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;health-soils-trap-and-retain-water&quot;&gt;Health Soils Trap and Retain Water&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lecture, in four parts, provides an introduction to soil tilth. It also highlights the importance of organic matter in building and maintaining health soils for agriculture. In the videos I provide an overview of tilth and soil concepts. And I describe some key influences organic matter has on slowing the water cycle. Together, tilth and organics are an option for water conservation. Please have a look at my introductory presentation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://agforinsight.com/agriculture-and-the-water-cycle/&quot;&gt;agriculture and water cycle&lt;/a&gt;, for more background on these concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video series concludes with some practical management guidance on options for adding and retaining soil organic matter. And it includes discussion on tillage, grazing, agroforestry and composting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tilth-and-organics-video-part-1&quot;&gt;Tilth and Organics Video, Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduces soil tilth, soil tilth indicators, and the importance of organic matter in building and maintaining tilth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/O5dGRtijQ5k?feature=oembed&quot; title=&quot;Tilth and Soil Organics for Water Conservation part 1&quot; width=&quot;640&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tilth-and-organics-video-part-2&quot;&gt;Tilth and Organics Video, Part 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of healthy soils and soil organic matter in farm water conservation is discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XhwZDJm7ANI?feature=oembed&quot; title=&quot;Tilth and Soil Organics for Water Conservation part 2&quot; width=&quot;640&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tilth-and-organics-video-part-3&quot;&gt;Tilth and Organics Video, Part 3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Options for direct additions of organic matter are described, with a discussion on the pros and cons of various organic matter sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tfVgLdCxREc?feature=oembed&quot; title=&quot;Tilth and Soil Organics for Water Conservation part 3&quot; width=&quot;640&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tilth-and-organics-video-part-4&quot;&gt;Tilth and Organics Video, Part 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indirect additions of soil organics through management (grazing, agroforestry, mulching) are described. Methods for retaining soil organic matter and maintaining good tilth are highlighted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JameGaVV61c?feature=oembed&quot; title=&quot;Tilth and Soil Organics for Water Conservation part 4&quot; width=&quot;640&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>George Powell</name></author><category term="Agriculture" /><category term="Agroforestry" /><category term="composting" /><category term="Organic" /><category term="organic matter" /><category term="soil" /><category term="soil conservation" /><category term="tillage" /><category term="tilth" /><category term="water" /><category term="water conservation" /><summary type="html">Videos highlight the importance of soil tilth and organic matter in maintaining healthy soil for water conservation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SoilTilthandOrganics-768x424.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SoilTilthandOrganics-768x424.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>